Where did we get this idea that
light-to-moderate drinking was
beneficial for health? Are there
any benefits? Watch to find out.
"Friday Favorites: Is It Better to Drink Little Alcohol Than None?
Do Any Benefits Outweigh Risks?"
Why do we not see the corporate
interests of the alcohol industry
as clearly as we see those
of the tobacco industry?
Well, the alcohol industry has waged
a sophisticated and successful campaign
over the last few decades, undermining
perceptions of the extent
of alcohol-related harm to health
by framing the argument as
a balance of benefits and harms.
Yes, alcohol may be an intoxicating
carcinogen, increasing cancer risk,
but what about reducing
heart disease risk?
Policymakers hesitate to introduce
effective alcohol policies,
or even to support the
addition of warning labels
for fear they might undermine or contradict
any possible health benefits of alcohol use.
After all, alcohol consumption clearly raises
HDL, the supposed "good" cholesterol.
But sadly, as I've already explored, HDL
is no longer considered protective,
based in part on so-called Mendelian
randomization studies,
where having a high HDL your whole
life doesn't appear to help,
whereas a lifelong reduction
of bad cholesterol, LDL,
just thanks to luck-of-the-draw genetics,
does indeed decrease heart disease risk.
So the boost in HDL from
alcohol may not matter,
and if you look at subclinical
markers of atherosclerosis,
like the thickening of the wall of
your carotid arteries in your neck,
those that abstain from alcohol completely
seem to be at the lowest risk,
and the same with coronary
calcium scores, where, in general,
the lower the alcohol consumption,
the lower the risk.
And alcohol bumps our blood
pressure up a bit as well,
which would be expected to
raise, not lower, our cardiac risk.
So where do we get this idea
that alcohol was good for us?
From the famous J curve.
Check it out.
If you follow large populations
of people over time, in general
the more people drink, the higher
their risk of dying prematurely,
but the lowest risk, those
who tend to live the longest,
were not those who drank
zero, the abstainers,
but those who drank moderately,
like one drink a day.
That's why you get some folks recommending
that physicians should counsel
lifelong nondrinkers to take up the habit.
Sure, there are statin drugs, but alcoholic
beverages don't require a prescription,
are far cheaper, and
certainly more enjoyable.
Is moderate drinking really protective,
or is there just something about people
who abstain completely from alcohol
that puts them in a higher risk category?
The reason we suspect
something fishy is going on
is that abstainers seem to be at higher
risk of a whole swath of diseases
including, ironically, liver cirrhosis.
Compared to lifelong abstainers,
those who've never touched the stuff,
men and women drinking a little
appear to have less liver cirrhosis.
Wait---what?
How could a little drinking be linked
to lower rates of liver cirrhosis?
Well, let's think about it.
What makes more sense,
that drinking lead to less liver cirrhosis
or liver cirrhosis lead to less drinking?
In other words, reverse causation,
the so-called sick quitter effect.
If you look at studies of smokers,
sometimes you see higher mortality rates
among those who quit smoking compared
to those that continue smoking.
Why? Because the reason they quit
smoking is because they got sick.
So, of course, sick people die
more often than less sick people.
That's why when you classify someone
as a non-smoker in a study,
you have to make sure
they're a lifelong non-smoker
and not just a non-smoker---
since last Tuesday.
Yet, unbelievably, that's not what
they do in most alcohol studies,
where instead they misclassify former
drinkers as if they were lifelong abstainers.
And, look, individuals with poorer
health are more likely to cut down
or stop drinking completely, thereby
making current drinkers look good
in comparison to those who drink zero,
because some of the abstainers
are just abstaining because
they got sick and stopped.
OK. So, what if you went
back to all those studies
and corrected the misclassifications,
separate out the former drinkers
from the lifelong abstainers?
We didn't know until now.
They, indeed, found drinker
misclassification errors all too common,
plaguing three quarters of the studies,
and when they controlled for that
the J-shaped curve disappeared.
The death versus alcohol relationship
became more consistent
with a straight line, linear dose response,
meaning more alcohol, more death:
no protection at low
levels of consumption.
So no apparent benefit of light
to moderate drinking after all,
when you use better comparison groups.
Although these results are not
what the majority of drinking
adults may desire to believe,
the public deserves to hear
and to read in more complete
and balanced detail
the ever-growing evidence
that drinking alcohol is very
unlikely to improve their health.
Once you remove from studies
on alcohol and mortality
the systematic error of misclassifying former
drinkers as if they were lifelong abstainers,
moderate alcohol consumption,
like a glass of wine a day,
does not appear to be protective after all.
The immediate implication
from this new research
is that clinicians need to be highly
skeptical about the hypothesized
health benefits of alcohol consumption
and should not advise their patients
to drink to improve their life expectancy.
This is especially important given
increasing awareness of cancer risks
from even moderate alcohol use.
Given the cancer risk, if there's
just harms and no benefits,
then the ideal alcohol intake on a routine
day-to-day basis should really be zero,
potentially making it a red-light beverage.
The problem was that many
of these population studies
classified those that quit drinking in
response to ill-health as nondrinkers.
This is the problem of reverse causation:
instead of abstaining leading to poor health,
poor health may have lead to abstaining.
It's like when studies show those who sit
around and watch TV have worse health.
Is more TV leading to illness,
or is illness leading to
more TV on the couch?
That's one of the reasons why if you
look at the hierarchy of evidence,
where higher on the pyramid
means stronger evidence,
interventional trials, like
randomized controlled trials,
tend to offer better evidence than
observational studies of populations,
which can suffer from both reverse
causation and confounding factors.
For example, light drinkers as a group may
be more likely to drink their glass of wine
with a salad than a cheeseburger, and
that's why the wine appeared protective.
But sometimes it's hard to do
randomized controlled trials,
like you can't randomize people to
smoke a pack a day for a few decades.
So sometimes you have to base your
decisions on observational studies.
But now we have a new tool,
Mendelian randomization.
In cases where randomized controlled
trials are not feasible or practical,
this new tool can provide reliable evidence
on the cause and effect relationship
between exposures and risks of disease.
It's like the HDL story.
Alcohol does raise your HDL
'good' cholesterol levels.
But unfortunately, it seems
good cholesterol isn't any good
at lowering heart disease risk after all,
based in part on Mendelian
randomization studies,
where people who were randomly assigned
higher HDL levels genetically from
birth don't appear to be protected.
Is there any way to study people
who are randomly assigned since conception
to not drink as much?
Remarkably, yes.
Alcohol is detoxified in the liver to carbon
dioxide and water by two enzymes.
But in the process, a toxic
intermediate metabolite is produced
called acetaldehyde, which can cause
unpleasant nausea and flushing sensations.
So if people are born with a
slow variant of this enzyme,
or a superfast variant of this enzyme,
acetaldehyde can build up,
making alcohol drinking in these people
a relatively unpleasant experience
throughout their lives.
So they're just born less likely to drink as much.
So do they have an increased
risk of heart disease,
like the original observational
studies would suggest?
No, they have reduced
risk of heart disease.
This suggests that reduction
of alcohol consumption,
even for light to moderate drinkers,
is beneficial for cardiovascular health.
So this just sheds further doubt
on the protective association
between 'moderate' alcohol
consumption and heart disease,
which was already plagued
with the confounding and bias.
And now the scientific pillars on which
it's based appear increasingly shaky,
leading some to suggest the leaning
tower of presumed health benefits
from 'moderate' alcohol
use has finally collapsed.
Given the harms attributed
to alcohol use,
it is not surprising that reports suggesting
benefits attracted enthusiasm
among consumers, the media,
and, of course, the alcohol industry,
but these apparent benefits
are now evaporating.
What conclusions should we draw
from this emerging evidence?
First, in health as elsewhere, if
something looks too good to be true
—like butter is back—
it should be treated with great caution.
Secondly, health professionals
should discourage drinking.
Thirdly, health advice should
come from health authorities,
not from the alcohol industry, which
should remove all misleading references
to purported health benefits, which
are increasingly looking more
like a triumph of spin doctoring
than good science,
as contrived as the alleged split
among scientists over climate change,
advanced by the petroleum industry.
As an intoxicating, addictive,
toxic, carcinogenic drug,
alcohol is not a great choice as a
therapeutic agent, even if it did help.
There are better ways
to prevent heart attacks,
namely diet and exercise,
and drugs when necessary.
In contrast to that of alcohol,
effectiveness of lifestyle interventions
has been demonstrated,
and as a bonus has no abuse potential.
There's a reason there's
no Appleholics Anonymous.